INSTRUCTOR: Hey all,
welcome to week 2.
This week, we're
going to continue
to build on what we learned
last week, especially
with those references and
building out our own formulas.
But this week, we're really
diving into this world that's
built on the idea of
true versus false.
And if you think of the
idea of true and false,
sometimes we'll think of
it maybe a little bit more
as right versus wrong.
But in this case, really,
we're just essentially saying,
is this equal to or meets
the criteria of something,
or if it does not?
Because what we can then do is
if we understand if something
meets our criteria,
then we can go ahead
and start to do these different
things with that information.
We can start to count
specific things.
We can start to add
certain things, instead
of going through and
trying to filter them out
individually and then sum them.
The value of a Boolean, which
is that true-or-false idea,
really lets us dive
in and establish
that kind of relationship.
This idea also comes
in into SQL when
you're doing WHERE statements,
because a WHERE statement
has that condition that
you're pulling in the data.
And usually, you're doing
something with the data.
And so this idea transcends
both of those topics.
So what are we doing today?
We're going to talk
about what a Boolean is.
We've already talked about it.
We're going to
talk about it more.
We're going to talk
about if statements.
If statements are honestly what
I personally do in Excel 85%
of the time.
15% of the other part
of it is lookups.
Lookups can start
getting you in trouble
if you start chaining them
together more than four or five.
You can do as many as you want,
but the more things you're
trying to convince it to look
up, and then the more things
you're embedding in if
statements, the more likely
you are to get Excel to crash.
So if you start to
find yourself falling
into the multiple chains of
ifs or a bunch of lookups,
at that point, it may be
better to transfer your data
into a tool like SQL
or Power BI that can
handle that a little better.
That's a little more robust.
But for the most
of the time, Excel
is going to be absolutely
great for your needs.
And we're going to do
COUNTIFs and SUMIFs.
That's going to rely on if
something is true or not.
Then we're going to either
count it or add it together.
And then lookups, which is
similar to a multi-table join
in SQL, which you'll get into
in probably two weeks from now.
But you'll get introduced
to this idea of data
can exist in multiple
places, but then we
want to pull it all together
in order to evaluate it.
In order to understand these
goals a little bit more,
we're going to answer
these 4 and 1/2 questions.
The first one is, how many
shares did all of our campaigns
receive?
Using the ad_events table, how
many likes did each time of day
receive?
And then we're going to ask
about how many impressions
happened on the weekend.
We're going to add
how much budget we
spent on short campaigns.
And then we're
also going to talk
about how many impressions users
made that were in a specific age
range.
So again, this is the same data
we were working with last week.
We're going to continue
to use this data as we
progress through the semester.
And first of all, we're just
going to go to ad events.
We're mostly going to be working
in this worksheet this week.
I've pasted my questions here
so that they're front of mind.
And we can really
start to see them.
But let's first look
at, how many shares did
all of our campaigns receive?
So I'm not doing any filtering.
I just care about if
something was shared
or not, which is
in this event type.
And so first thing I
need to do to process
that is see if a row of
data is a share or not.
What kind of event happened?
So that's where the
Boolean's come in.
We're going to see if this
is true or if this is false.
So we can do this a couple ways.
The first way is, again,
we're hitting this equal sign.
I'm referencing G2.
That's where my first event is.
I'm going to add another equal.
And you may be inclined
to just type "share."
And if I do that, I'm
going to get an error,
specifically because we need to
have-- just like we do in SQL--
we need to have our
quotations around it in order
for it to be read in as text,
because then it's like, OK,
I'm evaluating at this
group of characters.
And this specific order is
equal to this other group
of characters in
a specific order.
And like, in this case,
is not equal to share.
OK.
We're going to drag that down.
And you'll notice I don't have
"share" capitalized in my equal.
But I do have capitalized
in event type.
In this particular case, it
isn't really picky about it.
It's like, OK, yep, an S is an
S. I don't really care if it's
capital S or lowercase s.
And I'm going to
just click that down.
And this table has
400,000 rows of data.
So for you to go through
by hand and be like,
OK, this is a share.
This isn't a share.
This is going to be a
little time-consuming.
One of the other ways
we can figure this out,
is one of the ways we learned
last week where we came up,
and we added our filter.
And so in this
particular case, I
could just come up and then
scroll all the way down and see,
right here, I have
a count that says,
OK, I'm only looking
at the shares
because that's what I filtered.
I have 1,957.
So that's another way
we can do it to identify
how many shares we have.
But this Boolean is going to let
us take it another step further
because we'll be
able to start doing
some additional
calculations on it.
So now that I've registered
if these are true or false,
that's where this idea
of a COUNTIF comes in.
So I'm going to
type in my equals,
and I'm going to say COUNTIF.
Because what happens is maybe
I want to predominantly display
how many shares we have.
Or I might want
to use that number
and feed it into another
formula down the road.
So I'm not going to
be able to rely just
on that little
number at the bottom.
And I want to be able to
continue to update my data.
So as new campaigns
come in, I don't want
to have to recalculate that.
So if I have this COUNTIF,
as I add more data,
it's going to automatically
update my numbers for me.
And so how we set up COUNTIF is
we say the first thing is range.
And we can come up to
this fx, and it'll give us
a little bit more information.
So this range, it says
it counts the number
of cells within a range
that meet a given condition.
So that given condition right
is where we're saying it's true.
So my range is
going to be G. OK.
So my range is going
to be that G column.
And then my criteria
is going to be just
what we did in this
column H. But instead
of saying equal
share, if I do that,
it should give me
that it's invalid.
If I'm just doing this, , I
just need to put in share.
And you'll see
automatically, when
I'm working in the
formula bar, it tells me
what the answer is going to be.
And we know since we
already filtered it,
that that's the number I'm
looking for in this case.
So now I know how many
shares our campaign received,
all of our campaigns received.
A lot of times, though,
a lot of our questions
are going to be asking us to
evaluate more than one criteria.
In these cases, very
similarly to what we just did,
we're going to do something
called a COUNTIFs, with an "S"
at the end, because it's going
to evaluate multiple ifs.
So if I want to calculate how
many likes each time of day
received, I need to understand
this idea of AND versus OR.
So let's first consider if
each row is let's say morning.
And then the other one
we need to see is like,
and I want to evaluate if it's
a like provided in the morning.
So conceptually, let's
just think about this.
For this first row of
data, if you're just
looking at this one
of data, would you
say that it is both
morning and like?
You would not.
Because even though
it is a like,
it didn't happen in the
morning, it actually
happened in a
different time of day.
So we can start to build out
these multiple conditions.
So let's first-- I'm going
to have you pause the video
and evaluate if
each row-- again,
there's 400,000 rows of data--
is a morning time of day or not.
So how we would do that is
equal F2 is equal to "Morning."
And we'll double-click that.
That's my favorite way to do it.
Double-clicking autofills
our formula down.
But we do see that F3
is equal to warning.
And that gives us a true.
Now, do the same
thing for likes.
What we'll do is we'll
say our equal sign, like,
is equal to "Like."
And what do you
think this result
is going to be-- true or false?
Exactly, it's going to be true
because it is, in fact, a like.
And we don't see another
like for a while.
We have a lot more
impressions, which makes sense.
An impression is just
people scrolling by.
They stop, they saw it.
But that was the limit
of their interaction.
Going and actually
actively liking something,
sharing it, even going
through and purchasing
are a lot more concrete actions
than just how many times
it was viewed.
So now I need to
evaluate if it's
something that happened in both
the morning and was a like.
So what I'm going to do here
is I'm going to say AND.
And if you're doing
this in English,
you're going to say
it's morning and a like.
But in Excel syntax, AND
or ORs go on the outside.
Then we put that parentheses.
And again, you can always come
up and click the fx button.
And you can fill it in here.
So our first logic
is if H2 equals TRUE.
And our second is
if I2 equals TRUE.
And then we'll
autofill that down.
So we can do the same thing.
So I'm going to come
up here, and I'm
going to come to my filter.
And I'm going to check to see
how many times of day events
I've got.
In this case, I've got four.
It looks like I've got morning,
afternoon, evening, and night.
So I'm just going to
create a table over here.
And night.
And I'm going to start
this off very similarly
to what my other one was.
So COUNTIF.
But I have to evaluate
two conditions.
So in this particular case,
I'm doing my COUNTIFs.
And it looks very similar.
But I need to first say, OK,
let's look at time of day,
and then if that equals Morning.
And then my criteria range
2, if that equals Like.
And so in the morning, I have
2,981 likes that happened
in the morning.
So you may be tempted to start
dragging this formula over.
But see if you do
that, see if you
can figure out what the problem
was and if you can fix it.
So the problem is
our data continued
to shift over because we didn't
use any of those dollar signs
to lock in where they're going.
So I'm going to find
my blue, and I'm
going to drag it back over.
Find my purple.
Drag it back over.
And since I want to just be able
to drag my formula over instead
of retyping it over
and over again,
if I put my dollar
signs there, I
should be able to
now drag my formula.
And if I click on Night now,
nothing looks like it shifted.
So I'm good to go.
And now what I can see is
that, overall, my likes
fall within like maybe 100.
My range isn't that
big, but I can come back
and say, yeah, actually,
night is the most popular time
for people to be
liking our post.
Perfect.
Now, how many impressions
happened on the weekend.
So how many views
are we looking at?
So I want to create a new
column called Weekend.
And how would you
expect to do that?
So Weekend,
Saturday, and Sunday.
I have day of the
week data over here.
So if I say--
again, this goes back
to that AND or OR, which
do you think I need to use?
I need to use the OR because
I can't be both true Saturday
and true on Sunday.
It's only ever going to be
Saturday or Sunday in order
for me to label it the weekend.
And that's where this idea of if
comes into play really nicely.
And what if does is it says,
I'm going to do this test.
And if it's true, I'm
going to do something.
And if it's false, I'm
going to do this other thing
or just leave it blank.
So let's first just see
if Saturday is true.
So if this equals Saturday,
and I'm going to say "Weekend."
Else, I'm going
to say "Weekday."
And that works.
First, remember, we're just
evaluating for Saturday.
So right now, we're
labeling Sunday
as a weekday, which we're
going to want to change.
And we see that works
for Friday and Thursday.
So based off of what we just
did for our morning, afternoon,
evening, and night, go
ahead and make the change
that you think you need in
order to consider if it's
either Saturday or Sunday.
So hopefully, when you
are working on that,
we came to the conclusion
that we needed an OR.
And remember, even though
we string it together
in English in the
middle, we have
to put it on the outside in
Excel for it to evaluate it.
So OR, E2 is equal to Sunday.
And then a close parentheses.
So we're starting to nest
functions and formulas
within each other, which is
pretty typical for Excel.
So now let's do the same thing
and drag our formula down a few.
And now we see that Sunday
is also considered a weekend.
If we label this AND, everything
is going to actually be labeled
"Weekday," because Excel doesn't
intuitively know that Saturday
and Sunday is something
that we call weekend.
We're just saying that
this set of characters
has to be equal
to both Saturday.
And since we're looking at
the same reference cell,
it also has to be
equal to Sunday.
If that's not true,
then it has to be false.
And so that's why we're
getting weekday there
and why we need OR as
our operator there.
Perfect.
So now that we have our
weekend column built out,
how many impressions
happened on the weekend?
OK.
Go ahead and do
that calculation.
All right.
So now that you're
back, remember,
we need to use the
COUNTIFs, because I
need to use two different
conditions again.
So first one is I want to
see if it's a weekend or not.
Second, I want to see if my
event type is an impression.
And so we see that on
weekends, we have about 96--
almost 97,000 impressions
on a given weekend.
Perfect!
And now we'll go ahead
and move on to question 3.
So sum the total budget if the
project campaign was considered
short or less than 30.
So in this particular
case, this is actually
going to be found under
the Campaigns tab.
So SUMIF-- oops!
I'm going to sum my total budget
if my duration is less than--
so I'm going to SUMIF, and this
is the range I'm considering--
is less than 30 days.
Actually, I think our
lowest is more than 30.
Let's change that to
60 days, because I
don't think any campaign
was shorter than 30 days.
SUMIF our duration comma.
And I'm just following
along with what it's
asking me to do-- less than 60.
And then it's asking
me to sum my range.
And that's what I'm
actually going to be adding.
So I spent almost $843,000 on
campaigns that were considered
short.
That's quite a lot of money.
But it's the same thing.
So SUMIF works a
little differently
because our criteria, we're
able to point and say,
I want the criteria
based on column E,
but then I actually want you
to add the numbers in column F.
And then last but
not least, I want
to count how many impressions
users had if they were
in the 18 to 24 range mode.
So looking at our
data and ad_events--
and this is essentially how
we think about joins in SQL.
So in two weeks when you
get to it in data 2100--
if you're taking that,
alongside this course--
this should, hopefully, start
to feel a little familiar.
And we've already
talked about keys.
And so again, this is
that same idea of keys.
So I don't actually
have the age range here.
But I do know that
in my users table,
I do have this age group data.
And this is what I want
to combine in here.
Now, a user can have lots
of different interactions
with different campaigns.
And in my users table, I
have about 10,000 users.
So I do not want to go through
by hand and try to find that
user 99e3f--
is in the 35 to 45 range--
and do that for every single
one of my 400,000 rows.
That is not a good time.
And this is why we have tools.
And so that's what
a VLOOKUP does.
And the textbook
talks about HLOOKUP.
Definitely continue
to read that.
I've just found that VLOOKUPs is
95% of what I do in Excel when
it comes to lookups.
And so what we do, a
VLOOKUP and HLOOKUP,
is just where we're
looking for something.
So a VLOOKUP is a vertical--
up and down.
And so what I want to
do is I want to say,
I'm going to look up column C--
in this case, column C2.
And I want to find this
value in a table array.
And that table array is the
table we're trying to reference.
And pro tip,
whatever you select,
this needs to be
in the first row.
So your key needs to be in the
first-- sorry, the first column,
not the first row--
in order for it to
identify the lookup.
So the next argument
I need to include
is which column number I
actually want to return.
So I'm going to count.
So 1, 2, 3, 4.
So I want to look up column 4.
And I want it to
be an exact match.
Because if a user, for some
reason, isn't in my user table,
then we're not going
to worry about it.
And I'm going to
double-click that in.
So now we can see that we
have age range based off
of that VLOOKUP.
OK.
Let's go ahead and
practice this again.
Let's say I also want
to pull in their gender.
How would you go
ahead and do that?
Go ahead and pause
the video and try it.
So I'm going to do a
VLOOKUP the same way.
I'm going to click
on my user ID here
because I know that's the value
that exists in both tables.
And then I'm going to
highlight over here.
And in this case, I need one,
only my second column of data.
And again, I want
the exact match.
And now I have all of this
information pulled in in seconds
instead of trying
to manually compile
that information together.
So now I count how
many impressions users
made in that 18 to 24 range.
So let's go ahead and do it.
And that is going to be what
you turn in to this week.
Go ahead and submit the
answer to question 4.
Good luck with your
textbook reading.
I'm excited to see
how you're doing.
As always, please let me know
how I can help your learning
and make Excel an
exciting topic for you.